Business Correspondence of Smith, Elder, and Co., 1850-1908: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
Business Correspondence of Smith, Elder, and Co.
1850-1908
C0004
Princeton University Library. Special Collections. Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
0.4 linear feet 1 archival box
Smith, George, 1824-1901.
Consists, for the most part, of business correspondence of George Smith relating to the Cornhill Magazine, which he founded in 1859, and other publishing business of Smith, Elder, and Co., the London publishing firm.
The publishing firm of Smith, Elder, and Co. was founded by George Smith (1789–1846) and Alexander Elder (1790–1876). Upon the death of his father, George Smith (son) took control and under his stewardship, the company flourished. Its first major success was the publication of Charlotte Brontë's Jane Eyre in 1847, under the pseudonym of "Currer Bell." The firm is perhaps best known for publishing the first edition of the Dictionary of National Biography, widely popularized as the DNB.
The collection consists, for the most part, of business correspondence of George Smith relating to the Cornhill Magazine, which he founded in 1859, and other publishing business of Smith, Elder, and Co., the London publishing firm. Correspondents include Charles Allston Collins, Dutton Cook, James Hannay, William Gifford Palgrave, Russell Sturgis, Sir Henry Taylor, and Sir George Otto Trevelyan. In addition, there is a large folder of correspondence (1871-1874) with Edward Steinkopff and family, as well as one (1873-1874) with A. Donald Smith.
A group of 38 letters, the majority addressed to Reginald John Smith or Sir Leslie Stephen on similar literary business, were added more recently. Authors include Annie Besant, Egerton Castle, Percy Fitzgerald, Philip Bourke Marston, George Augustus Sala, and Halliwell Sutcliffe.
George Smith correspondence was purchased in October 1975.
Additional correspondence was purchased in March 2012.
No appraisal information is available.
Smith, A. Donald.; Steinkopff, Edward.; Smith, Elder, and Co.; Authors, English -- 19th century.; Publishers and publishing -- England -- 19th century.; Publishing history; Publishing history
- Correspondence: A-M, 1865-1874; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  AM 21739
- Correspondence: N-Z, 1865-1881; 1 folder (Folder 2)
- Ainer, Arthur Campbell, 4 May 1869; 1 folder (Folder 3)
- Besant, Annie, 7 February 1870; 1 folder (Folder 4)
- Bradley, Edward, 1863-1864; 1 folder (Folder 5)
- Brown, Oliver Madox, May 1873; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- Bullen, Frank Thomas, 3 January 1906; 1 folder (Folder 7)
- Castle, Egerton, 13 February 1912; 1 folder (Folder 8)
- Clarke, Edward George, Sir, 5 November 1908; 1 folder (Folder 9)
- Crockett, Samuel Rutherford, 6 June 1898; 1 folder (Folder 10)
- Dowden, Edward, 1 December 1882; 1 folder (Folder 11)
- Fitzgerald, Percy Hetherington, undated; 1 folder (Folder 12)
- Gissing, Algernon, 1915; 1 folder (Folder 13)
- Grenow, Rees Howell, 24 July 1864; 1 folder (Folder 14)
- Holyoake, George Jacob, 27 November 1869; 1 folder (Folder 15)
- Hutton, Richard Holt, undated; 1 folder (Folder 16)
- Hyne, Charles John Cutliffe Wright, 1894-1895; 1 folder (Folder 17)
- Jeaffreson, John Cordy, undated; 1 folder (Folder 18)
- Marston, Philip Bourke, undated; 1 folder (Folder 19)
- Martin, Theodore, Sir, 28 November 1872; 1 folder (Folder 20)
- Morley, John, 1862-1882; 1 folder (Folder 21)
- Norris, William Edward, 1877-1884; 1 folder (Folder 22)
- Robinson, Mary, undated; 1 folder (Folder 23)
- Sala, George Augustus, undated; 1 folder (Folder 24)
- Smith, A. Donald, 1873-1874; 1 folder (Folder 25)
- Smith, Geroge Barnett, undated; 1 folder (Folder 26)
- Snow, William Parker, 17 July 1876; 1 folder (Folder 27)
- Steinkopff, Edward, 1873-1874; 1 folder (Folder 28)
- Sutcliffe, Halliwell, 4 January 1912; 1 folder (Folder 29)
- Vizetelly, Henry, 1870; 1 folder (Folder 30)
- Walford, Edward, 21 November 1882; 1 folder (Folder 31)
- Miscellaneous, 1855-1870; 1 folder (Folder 32)
- 32101040795336 (Box 1)